<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="community-support">
  <title>Community support</title>

  <para>Many technologies and companies have a presence on the Internet
  for support and interaction between between users and developers.  This
  model of community support is particularly relevant for RTC technology.
  RTC, by definition, requires interoperability between all those using the
  technology and efficient online collaboration helps to identify and
  resolve interoperability problems.  Many users also have common problems
  to solve, such as the collaboration between Internet companies to
  eliminate spam.</para>

  <para>In the RTC domain, there are a range of online communities with
  various objectives.  The objectives include supporting specific pieces
  of software, development of standards, discussion of operational issues
  between providers and advocacy of open standards and private
  communication.</para>

  <sect1 id="community-support-mailing-lists">
    <title>Mailing lists</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Strategy and advocacy</title>

      <para>The
      <ulink url="https://lists.fsfe.org/mailman/listinfo/free-rtc">FSFE
      Free RTC mailing list</ulink> discusses strategies for promoting
      and adopting free RTC and free software.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Collaboration between operators and service providers</title>

      <para>The <ulink url="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/operators">
      XSF XMPP operators mailing list</ulink> enables discussion of issues
      between organizations managing XMPP servers of any size.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Server support</title>

      <para>The
      <ulink url="http://list.resiprocate.org/mailman/listinfo/repro-users">
      reSIProcate <code>repro</code> users mailing list</ulink> provides
      community support for people setting up and operating the
      <code>repro</code> SIP proxy server.</para>

      <para>The <ulink url="http://prosody.im/discuss#mailing_lists">Prosody
      users mailing list</ulink> provides community support for people
      setting up and operating the <emphasis>Prosody</emphasis> XMPP
      server.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Softphones</title>

      <para>The <ulink url="http://lists.lumicall.org">Lumicall users mailing
      list</ulink> supports users of the <emphasis>Lumicall</emphasis>
      Android app.</para>

      <para>The <ulink url="https://jitsi.org/Development/MailingLists">Jitsi
      users mailing list</ulink> provides a resource for those setting up
      and using the Jitsi products, including the popular Jitsi
      softphone.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="community-support-blogs-and-news">
    <title>Popular blogs and news sites</title>

    <para><ulink url="http://planet.sip5060.net">planet.sip5060.net</ulink>
    syndicates blogs from leading software developers with a focus on RTC
    and especially SIP.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
