<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
      xml:id="enum">
  <title>Adding ENUM to DNS</title>

  <para><emphasis>ENUM</emphasis> is a scheme described in RFC 6116 for
  mapping E.164 telephone numbers to SIP addresses, XMPP addresses and
  various other types of resource.  ENUM can enable more rapid discovery of
  services, network resilience and convenience for people who only have a
  telephone number or a numeric dialpad.</para>

  <para>Telephone numbers are everywhere.  People have large collections of
  phone numbers in their mobile telephone address books.  Many organizations
  have large databases of customer phone numbers that have either been
  submitted by customers or collected from caller-ID.  In public ENUM,
  the owner of a number is able to give callers specific options for
  contacting them.  In private ENUM, organizations can distribute a rich
  set of routing data in a highly efficient and convenient format, DNS.</para>

  <para><emphasis>ENUM</emphasis> must be considered from two perspectives:
  publishing your own data for <emphasis>ENUM</emphasis> users and making
  use of the <emphasis>ENUM</emphasis> data published by other people and
  organizations.</para>

  <sect1 xml:id="enum-how-enum-works">
    <title>How ENUM works</title>
    <para>ENUM works with numbers written in the <emphasis>ITU E.164</emphasis>
    notation.  For example, a London phone number may be dialed
    <code>020 7123 4567</code> from within the UK but its
    <emphasis>E.164</emphasis> representation is <code>+442071234567</code>.
    <emphasis>E.164</emphasis> numbers are always designated with a leading
    plus (<code>+</code>) symbol.  The digits following the plus symbol are
    the country prefix (<code>44</code> in the example) and then any area
    code and finally the local number itself.  Any other digits, such as the
    <code>0</code> used when dialing within the UK are not present.  You may
    have noticed this notation is used for incoming phone calls and text
    messages on your mobile phone.</para>

    <para>To perform an ENUM query, the first step is to take the number
    and normalize it into the <emphasis>ITU E.164</emphasis> format.
    Google's <emphasis>libPhoneNumber</emphasis>, a free software project,
    is an ideal tool for normalizing phone numbers individually or
    en-masse.</para>

    <para>Once you have the <emphasis>E.164</emphasis> number, remove the
    leading plus symbol, reverse the order of the digits and insert periods
    between them.  For the example number, it becomes
    <code>7.6.5.4.3.2.1.7.0.2.4.4</code>.</para>

    <para>The next step is to append the ENUM suffix.  The public ENUM suffix
    is <code>e164.arpa</code>.  To look up the example number in public ENUM,
    it would be written <code>7.6.5.4.3.2.1.7.0.2.4.4.e164.arpa</code>.
    Private and in-house ENUM services simply use an alternative suffix.  You
    may choose to perform multiple ENUM queries concurrently using different
    suffixes and then choose the best result.</para>

    <para>A DNS query is sent using the query string that has been constructed.
    The query requests <code>NAPTR</code> records.</para>

    <para>Finally, the ENUM algorithm must inspect the <code>NAPTR</code>
    records that have been returned and try to identify which, if any, are
    useful.  For example, if the query only returns a HTTP URL, a SIP proxy
    may not be able to use it and will ignore the result and use some other
    mechanism to route the call.</para>

    <para><xref linkend="enum-query-dig"/> demonstrates how to execute an
    ENUM query from the command line for the UK phone number
    <code>01865 332244</code> in the public ENUM suffix
    <code>e164.arpa</code>.</para>

    <example xml:id="enum-query-dig">
      <title>Using <code>dig</code> to perform ENUM queries</title>
      <programlisting format="linespecific">$ dig -t naptr 4.4.2.2.3.3.5.6.8.1.4.4.e164.arpa

; > DiG 9.8.4-rpz2+rl005.12-P1 > -t naptr 4.4.2.2.3.3.5.6.8.1.4.4.e164.arpa
;; global options: +cmd
;; Got answer:
;; ->>HEADER ;; flags: qr rd ra; QUERY: 1, ANSWER: 2, AUTHORITY: 3, ADDITIONAL: 4

;; QUESTION SECTION:
;4.4.2.2.3.3.5.6.8.1.4.4.e164.arpa. IN	NAPTR

;; ANSWER SECTION:
4.4.2.2.3.3.5.6.8.1.4.4.e164.arpa. 86400 IN NAPTR 100 20 "u" "E2U+pstn:tel" "!^(.*)$!tel:\\1!" .
4.4.2.2.3.3.5.6.8.1.4.4.e164.arpa. 86400 IN NAPTR 100 10 "u" "E2U+sip" "!^\\+441865332(.*)$!sip:\\1@nominet.org.uk!" .</programlisting>
    </example>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="enum-consume">
    <title>Consuming ENUM data</title>
    <para>ENUM data can be consumed at various points.</para>

    <para>The device or softphone where the user starts a call may have the
    ability to study the number the user has dialed and search for relevant
    data in ENUM.  The data obtained from ENUM can be presented to the
    user through the user interface.  The Android apps
    <emphasis>Lumicall</emphasis> and <emphasis>ENUMdroid</emphasis> both
    operate in this manner.</para>

    <para>SIP proxy servers and Session Border Controllers (SBCs) may also
    perform ENUM queries when deciding how to route a call.  In these cases,
    the device does not have a user interface to allow the user to choose
    from multiple results.  Typically, the routing system will only look
    for a SIP address in the ENUM results and will automatically send the
    call there rather than sending it to a PSTN gateway.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="enum-publish">
    <title>Publishing ENUM data</title>
    <para>Setting up <emphasis>ENUM</emphasis> as part of your RTC deployment,
    in the public ENUM tree, an internal ENUM tree or both, are optional
    steps that provides more flexibility and resilience for routing
    calls.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Public ENUM</title>
      <para>In various countries, it is possible to have your phone
      numbers registered in the public ENUM tree for <code>e164.arpa</code>.
      Wikipedia maintains a
      <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Telephone_number_mapping#External_links">
      detailed list of national ENUM registries</link>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Private and third-party ENUM suffixes</title>
      <para>Even if your country does not have a national ENUM scheme yet,
      many large organizations are operating an internal ENUM service.
      If you have a domain name server, you can create <code>NAPTR</code>
      records in the zone files just as easily as creating an <code>A</code>
      or <code>CNAME</code> record.  It is relatively easy to construct a
      script using Python or Java to read from a company telephone directory
      and write a zone file for the name server.  The file can be regenerated
      periodically by a <code>cron</code> job.</para>

      <para>If your phone numbers are available in a local LDAP server, the
      <link xlink:href="http://www.opentelecoms.org/dlz-ldap-enum">dlz-ldap-enum
      </link> module can be used in a <emphasis>Bind9</emphasis> DNS name
      server to support real-time queries.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Dynamic ENUM from LDAP with <code>dlz-ldap-enum</code></title>
      <sect3>
        <title>Installation</title>
        <para>Install the package using the appropriate tool, as demonstrated
        in <xref linkend="dlzldapenum-install-debian"/> and
        <xref linkend="dlzldapenum-install-redhat"/>.</para>

        <example xml:id="dlzldapenum-install-debian">
          <title>Installing <code>dlz-ldap-enum</code> on Debian/Ubuntu</title>
          <programlisting format="linespecific">$ sudo apt-get install dlz-ldap-enum</programlisting>
        </example>

        <example xml:id="dlzldapenum-install-redhat">
          <title>Install <code>dlz-ldap-enum</code> on Fedora/RHEL/CentOS</title>
          <programlisting format="linespecific">$ sudo yum install dlz-ldap-enum</programlisting>
        </example>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Configuration</title>

        <para>The configuration file is <code>dlz_ldap_enum.conf</code>.  On
        a Debian/Ubuntu system, it can be found in <code>/etc/bind</code>
        while Fedora/RHEL/CentOS users will find it in
        <code>/etc/named</code>.</para>

        <para>The first step is to customize the file to specify the exact
        location of the plugin, the ENUM DNS suffix and your LDAP server
        connection parameters, as demonstrated in
        <xref linkend="dlzldapenum-config-sample"/>.</para>

        <example xml:id="dlzldapenum-config-sample">
          <title>Sample <code>dlz_ldap_enum.conf</code></title>
          <programlisting format="linespecific">dlz "example" {
    database "dlopen /usr/lib/dlz-ldap-enum/dlz_ldap_enum.so 2
        v3 simple {cn=admin,dc=example,dc=org} {secret} {127.0.0.1}
        e164-addr.example.org
        {localhost. root.example.org. 2 604800 86400 2419200 604800}
        localhost
        60
        ldap:///ou=$zone$,dc=example,dc=org???objectclass=top
        ldap:///dc=example,dc=org?mail?sub?telephoneNumber=$record$";
};</programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>Now add a reference to this file into the main
        <code>named.conf</code>, which may be under <code>/etc/bind</code> or
        just <code>/etc</code> depending upon your system.  This is
        demonstrated in
        <xref linkend="dlzldapenum-named-config-sample-debian"/> and
        <xref linkend="dlzldapenum-named-config-sample-redhat"/>.</para>

        <example xml:id="dlzldapenum-named-config-sample-debian">
          <title>Additions to <code>named.conf</code> for Debian/Ubuntu</title>
          <programlisting format="linespecific">include "/etc/bind/dlz_ldap_enum.conf";</programlisting>
        </example>

        <example xml:id="dlzldapenum-named-config-sample-redhat">
          <title>Additions to <code>named.conf</code> for Fedora/RHEL/CentOS</title>
          <programlisting format="linespecific">include "/etc/named/dlz_ldap_enum.conf";</programlisting>
        </example>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

</chapter>
