<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
      xml:id="optimal-connectivity">
  <title>Optimizing Connectivity</title>

  <para>People who have tried many of the free RTC softphones have observed
  that they don't always work through firewalls or NAT networks.  Sometimes
  these problems give visual feedback, in the form of error messages
  advising that the call can't proceed.  In other cases, the call appears
  to be connected but audio only works in one direction or stops after
  some brief period of time.</para>

  <para>Metcalfe's law tells us that the value of a telecommunications
  network is proportional to the square of the number of connected users
  of the system (n<superscript>2</superscript>).</para>

  <para>Therefore, the benefit of making the solution work for all those
  users who may suffer in certain NAT environments does not just have a
  gradual or linear impact, the benefit is quadratic.</para>

  <para>Today's RTC technology gives us the tools to deal with these
  problems in the vast majority of cases.  This chapter gives an overview
  of the main concerns.</para>

  <sect1 xml:id="optimal-connectivity-codecs">
    <title>Codec selection</title>

    <para>Codec is a portmanteau of coder-decoder.  A codec is an algorithm
    for encoding an audio or video signal for storage or transmission over
    a digital communications network.  Codecs are responsible for
    compression of the data stream and may also take some responsibility
    for error correction, packet loss concealment and silence
    suppression.</para>

    <para>Each device or softphone typically has one or more codec
    algorithms included.  Some software, such as the Asterisk PBX, can
    support additional codecs with the help of modules or plugins.</para>

    <para>The list of codecs supported by a product depends on the age of
    the product, patents and the type of products it is intended to
    interact with.  Open source solutions generally avoid patented codecs,
    although unofficial implementations of them can be found online,
    such as the popular G.729 codec for Asterisk.</para>

    <table xml:id="codecs-list">
      <title>Common codecs</title>
      <tgroup cols="5">
        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*" />
        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*" />
        <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1*" />
        <colspec colname="c4" colnum="4" colwidth="1*" />
        <colspec colname="c5" colnum="5" colwidth="3*" />

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry align="center">Name</entry>
            <entry align="center">Type</entry>
            <entry align="center">Bitrate (kbps)</entry>
            <entry align="center">Patented</entry>
            <entry align="center">Comments</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>G.711 (alaw, ulaw)</entry>
            <entry>audio</entry>
            <entry>64</entry>
            <entry>N</entry>
            <entry>Widely supported in phones, WebRTC browsers, ISDN gateways
            and virtually everywhere else.  Quality of traditional phone
            calls.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>G.722</entry>
            <entry>audio</entry>
            <entry>64</entry>
            <entry>N</entry>
            <entry>Supported in most modern software and high quality desk
            phones.  Transmits higher quality wideband audio in the same
            64kbps bandwidth used by G.711</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Opus</entry>
            <entry>audio</entry>
            <entry>6 - 510</entry>
            <entry>N</entry>
            <entry>Support in more modern software, WebRTC browsers and some
            very recent desk phones.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>G.729</entry>
            <entry>audio</entry>
            <entry>8</entry>
            <entry>Y</entry>
            <entry>A low bitrate codec supported in a lot of older VoIP phones
            and related hardware.  Voice quality less than a standard
            telephone call.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>G.723.1</entry>
            <entry>audio</entry>
            <entry>5.3, 6.3</entry>
            <entry>Y</entry>
            <entry>An ultra-low bitrate codec support in some older VoIP
            phones and related hardware.  Voices sound very bad.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>GSM full rate</entry>
            <entry>audio</entry>
            <entry>13</entry>
            <entry>N</entry>
            <entry>The original codec for GSM mobile telephony.  Supported in
            many older open source products and some VoIP hardware.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>iLBC</entry>
            <entry>audio</entry>
            <entry>15</entry>
            <entry>N</entry>
            <entry>A codec developed for Internet use before Opus.  Supported
            in many older open source products but not widely supported in
            VoIP hardware.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>speex</entry>
            <entry>audio</entry>
            <entry>2-44</entry>
            <entry>N</entry>
            <entry>A codec developed for Internet use before Opus.  Supported
            in many older open source products but not widely supported in
            VoIP hardware.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>VP8</entry>
            <entry>video</entry>
            <entry>depends</entry>
            <entry>N</entry>
            <entry>Mandatory part of WebRTC, supported in browsers.  Bitrate
            depends on resolution and frame rate.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>H.264</entry>
            <entry>video</entry>
            <entry>depends</entry>
            <entry>Y</entry>
            <entry>Mandatory part of WebRTC, supported in browsers and in
            many existing video conferencing hardware products.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

    </table>

    <para>The person configuring the software or device can typically
    select which codecs are permitted and also specify which codecs are
    preferred over others.</para>

    <para>When a call is made, the endpoints negotiate to select a codec
    that is supported at both ends.  If both endpoints have no codecs in
    common, the call is not possible and the user may see a message
    telling them the call failed.  If both endpoints have more than one
    codec in common, the exact codec selected in this negotiation algorithm
    depends on the relative priorities specified by the administrators
    of each endpoint.</para>

    <para>Some software has the ability to dynamically change the list
    of permitted codecs.  For example, some mobile apps will only enable
    high-bandwidth codecs when they detect the mobile device is using wifi
    or a 4G/LTE network.</para>

    <para>More modern codecs support a variable bit rate that can be
    changed automatically during a call to adapt to poor network conditions.
    The Opus codec used for WebRTC has this capability.</para>

    <sect2 xml:id="optimal-connectivity-codecs-recommendations">
      <title>Recommendations</title>

      <para>Enable as many codecs as possible to maximize the chance of
      connection.  This reduces the number of calls where the endpoints
      fail to find a common set of codecs.</para>

      <para>Disable those codecs that won't possibly work given the available
      bandwidth.  For example, in a remote location with a 128kbit DSL
      broadband connection it is usually necessary to disable 64kbit codecs
      like G.711 and G.722 and use codecs that have lower audio quality
      such as Opus, GSM and G.729.</para>

      <para>However, in a location with good bandwidth, don't disable the
      low-bit rate/low-quality codecs.  They will still be needed when
      calling a user who doesn't have great bandwidth.</para>

      <para>Order the remaining codecs based on the quality, with the
      best quality codec first. G.711 is typically present for
      compatibility but other codecs like G.722 offer better quality for
      the same amount of bandwidth, so rate G.722 ahead of G.711 and
      G.722 will be used whenever possible.</para>

      <para>Example 1: a mobile app: enable, in order of priority
      starting with the most preferred: Opus, Silk and GSM codecs.</para>

      <para>Example 2: a soft PBX in an office accessed by local users
      and mobile users: enable, in order of priority starting with the
      most preferred: Opus, G.722, G.711, Silk, iLBC, GSM, G.729.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="optimal-connectivity-rtp-encryption">
    <title>Media stream encryption compatibility</title>

    <para>RTC voice and video (media) streams are almost always
    transmitted using Real Time Protocol (RTP).</para>

    <para>Encrypting RTP streams is a popular requirement.  Some organizations
    are subject to regulations requiring encryption.  In other cases,
    there is a commercial imperative to use encryption.  Just as HTTP
    sessions can be encrypted with HTTPS, RTP streams can be encrypted
    using SRTP.  SRTP is optimized for the real-time nature of the media
    stream and it permits packet loss.</para>

    <para>While SRTP itself is relatively standard, there are several
    different ways to exchange keys for an SRTP session.  If the two
    endpoints trying to setup a call are not trying to use the same
    method for key exchange, or if one of them hasn't enabled encryption
    at all, <emphasis>the call will not connect</emphasis>.
    To meet our goal of maximizing connectivity, these mismatches must
    be avoided.</para>

    <para>The original method of key exchange for SRTP involves exchanging
    SDES keys through the signalling channel, which may be a SIP or XMPP
    connection.  Most of the original products supporting this standard
    take an all-or-nothing approach: if encryption is disabled,
    they will only talk to other endpoints without encryption and if
    encryption is enabled, they will only talk to other endpoints
    capable of the same key exchange protocol.</para>

    <para>One disadvantage of sending the keys through the signalling
    channel is that the operator of the SIP proxy can easily observe
    the keys and use them to decrypt the RTP streams.  Another risk
    is that the end-user has no way to know if a man-in-the-middle
    has swapped the keys, decrypting the streams, recording or modifying
    them and then sending them on to the other endpoint using a different
    key.  Two alternative solutions to these problems have emerged.</para>

    <para>Phil Zimmerman, the legendary creator of PGP encryption,
    created the ZRTP key exchange protocol.  When the endpoints support
    ZRTP, they typically send signalling messages (SDP) specifying that
    regular, unencrypted RTP will be used for the call.  When the
    call is answered, each endpoint tries to send some special ZRTP
    "hello" packets to the peer on the port normally used for the RTP.
    At this stage, the phones will indicate to the users that they are
    in a call without encryption.  If the endpoints both support ZRTP
    then they recognize the "hello" packets from the peer and they
    perform a key exchange using the Diffie-Hellman algorithm.  Once
    the key exchange is completed, the interface on the phone changes
    somehow to advise the user that the call is now encrypted.
    Due to the nature of the Diffie-Hellman algorithm and the verification
    of the algorithm by a short authentication string (SAS) that the users
    read to each other, the keys can not be observed or substituted by
    any man-in-the-middle.</para>

    <para>Nonetheless, the use of the SAS may appear slightly geeky and
    it is only valid if you know the other person personally and can
    <emphasis>recognize their voice</emphasis> when they are reading the
    SAS to you.  If you are calling an organization, such as the call
    center at the bank or a Government department, the person you are
    speaking to is likely to be a complete stranger, you will not have
    be familiar with the sound of their voice when they read the SAS
    and so you will not be able to rely on this algorithm.</para>

    <para>The DTLS-SRTP standard provides another alternative,
    although on its own, it does not provide certainty that there is
    no man-in-the-middle.  DTLS-SRTP provides a way to use DTLS key
    agreement before starting SRTP media streams.  To provide security
    against a man-in-the-middle, DTLS-SRTP can be combined with another
    mechanism for the exchange of key fingerprints.  For example, RFC 5763
    specifies a mechanism for exchanging tamper-proof key fingerprints
    in SDP using SIP Identity (RFC 4474).</para>

    <para>DTLS-SRTP is the mechanism that has been chosen for the WebRTC
    standard and it is widely implemented in web browsers.  It is also
    supported by the Asterisk and FreeSWITCH projects and some softphones
    including Jitsi.</para>

    <para>ZRTP is also supported in a number of products, including
    Asterisk, FreeSWITCH and the Jitsi softphone.  ZRTP is not currently
    supported in WebRTC browsers although it is preferred by products
    that focus on the privacy of personal communication between
    people who know each other, such as the Lumicall app.</para>

    <sect2 xml:id="optimal-connectivity-rtp-encryption-multi">
      <title>Supporting multiple schemes</title>

      <para>For encryption to be effective, users must know when it is
      working.  For this reason, many products started out with a
      simple all-or-nothing approach.  If the encryption setting is
      enabled, the product will only permit calls to and from peers using
      them same encryption settings.  Users could then conclude that any
      call that connects successfully is encrypted correctly.</para>

      <para>Furthermore, the way that an SDP offer/answer exchange is
      designed, a media descriptor either has crypto attributes or it
      doesn't.  There is no simple way for an endpoint to insert
      the attributes in the SDP and hint that they are optional.
      If they are present, the peer must act as if they are mandatory
      and reject the call if it is not capable of using encryption.
      </para>

      <para>Some phones have an option to send two media descriptors in SDP,
      one of them with crypto attributes and the other without.  However,
      some other phones don't understand this type of SDP and reject the
      call completely, so it is not a reliable strategy.</para>

      <para>Some phones have an option to try the call with encryption
      enabled and if it is rejected, automatically try again without
      encryption.  This strategy is not glamorous but it has wider
      compatibility.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="optimal-connectivity-rtp-encryption-recommendations">
      <title>Recommendations for maximizing connectivity</title>

      <para>Generally, SDES SRTP should be avoided and should not enabled
      except for very specific cases.  Do not enable SDES SRTP for arbitrary
      calls across the Internet as a means to improve compatability: the
      risks outweigh the benefits.  The cases where you may use SDES SRTP
      include situations where you have IP phones that don't support any
      other form of encryption and connections to SIP trunking providers
      who don't support any other form of encryption.  In these special
      cases, ensure that the SDES SRTP calls are only possible for
      the specific IP addresses or SIP accounts that you designate.
      Note that when you configure a connection profile in the PBX to use
      this encryption mode with certain peers, it may not be able to use
      the same connection profile for any other peers who don't use
      SDES SRTP.  This is the all-or-nothing scenario.</para>

      <para>When making calls, do not try to use the approach that involves
      sending multiple media descriptors, one with crypto attributes
      and the other without.  For all other calls, use software that tries
      to make the call using DTLS-SRTP and if that fails retries the call
      using ZRTP.  If encryption is not essential for you, allow calls
      to proceed even when ZRTP does not secure a connection.</para>

      <para>When receiving calls, be willing to accept calls using either
      DTLS-SRTP or ZRTP and possibly without any encryption at all, depending
      upon your requirements.  A SIP proxy can inspect the SDP to determine
      which type of encryption is attempted and route the call appropriately.
      For example, depending upon which attributes are present, the SIP
      proxy could route the call to an Asterisk <literal>sip.conf</literal>
      profile with DTLS-SRTP support or to another profile with ZRTP support.
      Alternatively, you may use a softphone that is capable of recognizing
      and accepting either type of encryption.</para>

      <para>Throughout this guide, we present further details about how
      to achieve all of the above with the products described herein.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="optimal-connectivity-rtp-encryption-recommendations-sec">
      <title>Recommendations for security</title>

      <para>The recommendations in the previous section will help optimize
      connectivity, by enabling more calls to connect successfully.
      Additional steps are required to ensure you fully benefit from the
      security that encryption can provide, these are described here.</para>

      <para>If you are enabling and relying on DTLS-SRTP with SIP, make sure
      you also use SIP Identity (RFC 4474) and use SIP Identity to
      authenticate the key fingerprints (RFC 5763).</para>

      <para>If you pass calls through intermediate network components
      such as Session Border Controllers or a PBX where the media streams
      are decrypted and re-encrypted, you need to think carefully about
      the impact on authentication.  For example, you may configure the PBX
      to enforce identity verification and then tell users that all calls
      that have come through the PBX can be trusted.</para>

      <para>If using phones or softphones that are configured to work
      with or without encryption (this is referred to as
      <emphasis>opportunistic encryption</emphasis>), it is very desirable
      for them to give the user an indication about whether each
      call is encrypted.  Otherwise, the user should be told to assume
      that calls are not encrypted.</para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="optimal-connectivity-turn">
    <title>Use ICE and a TURN server</title>
    <para>A TURN server provides a standard way to relay media on behalf
    of users who are stuck on a NAT network.  The Interactive Connectivity
    Establishment (ICE) protocol uses the TURN server to help explore
    network topology and give immediate feedback if the call is not possible,
    eliminating the menace of ghost calls.</para>

    <para>Several TURN servers are now available in convenient Linux packages,
    see <xref linkend="turn"/> for details about selecting and installing
    one.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="optimal-connectivity-tls">
    <title>Use the TLS transport for SIP packets</title>
    <para>When SIP packets are sent over UDP, there are several things
    that go wrong.  The first problem is that large SIP messages can be
    fragmented by the IP stack and some fragments are not delivered.</para>

    <para>When ICE is used, the SIP packet contains a larger SDP body to
    encapsulate the ICE candidates.  When a softphone attempts a video call,
    the combination of the video and audio descriptors further enlarges
    the SDP.  More and more frequently in modern RTC deployments, SIP
    packets sent over UDP exceed the maximum transmission unit and are
    subject to fragmentation.  IP packet fragments are not always routed
    correctly by other intermediate network components.  This was not a
    problem in the early days of SIP when the vast majority of devices only
    supported a limited number of audio codecs and overall packet sizes
    were well under one kilobyte.</para>

    <para>A more obscure issue is the presence of routers in homes and
    small offices that claim to have <emphasis>SIP helper</emphasis>
    capabilities.  These routers try to modify the SIP packets to help
    them through NAT.  In reality, the modifications made by the router
    can clash with the ICE protocol or other NAT discovery techniques
    used by the phone or the server.</para>

    <para>Sending all the SIP packets over a TLS connection eliminates all
    of these problems.  While there is slightly more effort involved to
    create a certificate for the server, it saves an enormous amount of
    ongoing support effort.</para>

    <para>See <xref linkend="tls"/> for details about creating the TLS
    certificates for SIP and XMPP.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="optimal-connectivity-firewalls">
    <title>Getting through firewalls</title>
    <para>When a user is in a developed country, at their home or using a
    mobile Internet connection, they may be behind a NAT router but the
    firewall on these devices is usually very permissive for connections
    initiated by the user.  In the vast majority of cases, the user will be
    able to initiate outbound TCP connections to any destination (such as
    a SIP, XMPP or WebSocket server on any arbitrary port number) and will
    be able to send and receive UDP.</para>

    <para>For some NAT routers, the UDP flows will only work reliably when
    the peer is using a public IP address.  This problem is automatically
    detected by ICE connectivity checks and it is resolved by sending the
    UDP packets through the TURN server.</para>

    <para>For users with more repressive Internet providers, in some less
    sophisticated wifi hotspots and in some corporate networks there are
    more aggressive firewall policies.  With a little care, the RTC
    deployment can be designed to work reliably in many of these
    environments too.</para>

    <para>The first issue is the signalling connection, whether it is SIP,
    XMPP or WebSockets.  More restricted corporate networks block
    outgoing TCP connections, except for those on port 80 or 443, which
    they redirect to a transparent proxy.</para>

    <para>As a consequence of this TCP blocking, it should be anticipated
    that the user's softphone may need to use the HTTP proxy for all RTC
    traffic, including media streaming and signalling.</para>

    <para>HTTP Proxy servers have a number of issues.  Older proxy servers
    do not understand the WebSocket protocol and newer proxy servers are
    not always configured to allow the WebSocket protocol by default.
    To avoid these problems, it is recommended that the WebSocket
    connection should always use TLS (WebRTC clients uses a
    <code>wss://</code> URL instead of a <code>ws://</code> URL) and the
    port 443 only.  Many HTTP proxies are correctly configured to allow
    the web browser to use the HTTP <code>CONNECT</code> method to
    initiate pass-through connections to <code>https://</code> URLs using
    the default port, 443.  Sometimes, however, the HTTP proxy does not
    allow any port other than 443.  Thanks to the encryption provided by
    TLS, the proxy server can not observe whether the HTTP
    <code>CONNECT</code> method is being used to reach a web server, a
    SIP server, a WebSocket server or even something else such as an
    <code>ssh</code> server.  Therefore, all services, including SIP over
    TLS, XMPP client connectivity (<code>c2s</code>), TURN over TLS and
    WebSockets, should listen on port 443 so that any of them can be
    reached by a user stuck behind a HTTP proxy.</para>

    <para>The next issue is the transmission of UDP.  In some networks,
    users simply can not exchange any UDP packets with external hosts.
    The only resolution to this issue is to tunnel the UDP packets through
    TCP.  Fortunately, the TURN server can also assist, as the TURN
    specification includes support for tunneling packets through a TLS
    connection.  To maximize the chance of success, it is recommended that
    the TURN server is also configured to listen on port 443 so that the
    connection to the TURN server will be able to pass through HTTP proxy
    servers using the HTTP <code>CONNECT</code> method.</para>

    <para>This strategy often requires several different processes (the
    standard SIP server, the XMPP <code>c2s</code> service, the webserver
    hosting a WebRTC phone, the WebSocket server and the TURN server) to
    all listen on the same port, 443.  For multiple processes to use the
    same port, it is necessary to either have a different public IP
    address for each process or to use a solution for port multiplexing,
    such as the <emphasis>sslh</emphasis> daemon.</para>

    <para>With these strategies, connectivity will be possible for the
    vast majority of Internet users, whether at home, at the office or
    on the road.</para>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
