<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
      xml:id="pbx">
  <title>PBX Setup</title>

  <para>A soft PBX (such as Asterisk or FreeSWITCH) provides features
  such as voicemail, menu systems and call queues.  Many of the typical
  features in a soft PBX have a particular focus on voice communications,
  rather than other types of RTC such as IM or video.</para>

  <para>It is perfectly feasible to build an RTC environment without these
  features.  It is recommended that a SIP proxy is used to handle all
  connectivity with users and any external parties, the reasons for this
  are explained in <xref linkend="rtc-architecture-sip-proxy"/>.  This
  also means that it is better to install and test the SIP proxy before
  making decisions about the selection and design of the soft PBX.</para>

  <para>The soft PBX can be configured to make a SIP registration in
  the SIP proxy or routing entries can be created in both the SIP proxy
  and soft PBX to send calls back and forth between them as required.</para>

  <para>The configuration and operation of soft PBXes tends to replicate
  many concepts from the world of traditional telephony.  The fact that
  many of the features of these products are voice-orientated is an
  example of this trend.  Many guides on soft PBX configuration tend to
  focus on the use of dial plans and phone numbers as the dominant
  currency in the world of legacy communications, while modern
  unified communications strategies involve <literal>user@domain</literal>
  addressing similar to other Internet-based services.</para>

  <sect1 xml:id="pbx-all-in-one-myth">
    <title>The all-in-one myth</title>

    <para>It is tempting to look at a soft PBX as a one-stop-shop for VoIP,
    with no other product required.  In fact, this is a very limited
    strategy in terms of features and resilience.</para>

    <para>Many people have a requirement to use existing ISDN lines
    with their RTC architecture.  With Asterisk and FreeSWITCH both
    boasting ISDN support, it is tempting to do everything with that
    single instance of a soft PBX installed on a server with ISDN hardware.
    </para>

    <para>Modularity is a hallmark of good design in any IT project.
    Modularity gives you the flexibility to upgrade or modify one component
    of a system without changing any other component.  Modularity also
    means that some components are more likely to continue providing
    service even if something fails.  In the planning of a soft PBX deployment,
    modularity involves running one instance of the soft PBX just to
    control the ISDN hardware and running another instance for services
    such as voicemail and using a SIP proxy to route calls between these
    different components.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="pbx-asterisk-or-freeswitch">
    <title>Choosing between Asterisk and FreeSWITCH</title>

    <para>Asterisk is by far one of the most well known open source
    VoIP server products.  It has a plethora of features and supports a
    diverse range of connectivity options, from IP based solutions like SIP
    to legacy technologies like ISDN and POTS.</para>

    <para>FreeSWITCH is a popular alternative to Asterisk,
    boasting many of the same features, but with a collective ownership
    model rather than the corporate model that is intertwined with
    Asterisk's licensing and contributor agreements.</para>

    <para>We consider some of the points where they differ.  Not every
    point is relevant in every deployment.</para>

    <para>If you are not sure which way to go and if maintaining the soft PBX
    will not be the primary focus of your job, we suggest using Asterisk
    because it has official packages but we do not wish to discourage
    people from considering FreeSWITCH when they understand the issues
    involved and feel it is the better choice.</para>

    <sect2 xml:id="pbx-asterisk-or-freeswitch-packaging">
      <title>Official packages</title>

      <para>Asterisk has officially supported packages in many of the popular
      GNU/Linux distributions.  FreeSWITCH does not.</para>

      <para>FreeSWITCH users have to use unofficial packages from the
      FreeSWITCH web site or compile from source code.  When packages are
      made available through an official distribution, like Debian or
      EPEL, it means they go through a managed release cycle and are
      subject to a battery of independent tests to ensure the packages
      don't interfere with any other packages on the same system.
      </para>

      <para>When something is available in an official package, it
      also means upgrading the operating system (for example, from
      Debian 7 to Debian 8) should also upgrade the package in a safe
      manner.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="pbx-asterisk-or-freeswitch-contributing">
      <title>Contributing patches</title>

      <para>Many more experienced users of open source software become
      intimitely familiar with the software they rely on and sometimes
      they even develop bug fixes or improvements.  It can be tedious
      to test and re-apply such fixes to each new version of a product
      and so many people in this situation usually want to contribute their
      fix to the primary source repository for the project so it will
      automatically be part of all future releases.</para>

      <para>Some projects welcome these contributions unconditionally
      and without any specific legal agreement, ownership of the
      contribution remains the intellectual property of the contributor
      and other members of the community are simply licensed to use it.
      </para>

      <para>Some projects ask the contributor to go a step further,
      giving the founders of the projects some additional rights to include
      the contribution in commercial products without releasing the source
      code of the final product.</para>

      <para>Finally, some projects go all the way and don't just ask the
      contributor for a preferential license, they ask the contributor
      to grant ownership of all intellectual rights in the contribution
      to the project's founders or some other entity.</para>

      <para>Asterisk is in second category, asking contributors to give
      Digium, the company behind Asterisk, a license to redistribute the
      contributions under alternative terms.  Some projects use this strategy
      to collect intellectual property rights in a non-profit community
      foundation but in this case the rights are being granted to Digium, 
      a company with shareholders.  Another point of contention is that
      the agreement is one-sided: it does not contain any commitment by
      Digium to release future versions of the product under any open source
      license.</para>

      <para>Some contributors are uncomfortable with these contribution terms
      and some people are unable to make contributions under these terms
      without violating regulations set by their own employer or funding
      they receive from public sources.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="pbx-asterisk-or-freeswitch-licensing">
      <title>Licensing</title>

      <para>Asterisk is distributed under the GPL while FreeSWITCH
      is using the Mozilla Public License.</para>

      <para>The main distinction between these licenses applied to those
      users who intend to build their own product around the soft PBX
      and sell it.  The GPL typically requires people in this situation
      to either publish the source code of any fixes or enhancements or
      other components they create as part of their overall solution.
      Digium has a parallel-licensing strategy, allowing people in this
      situation to pay a license fee and eliminate the obligations of the
      GPL.</para>

      <para>The Mozilla Public License used by FreeSWITCH doesn't involve
      these issues.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="pbx-asterisk-or-freeswitch-community">
      <title>Community</title>

      <para>The contributor agreement and the licensing strategy have an
      impact on the type of community that is forming around each product,
      especially the community of developers contributing to the products.
      </para>

      <para>Even for users who don't intend to either contribute source code
      or resell products built from Asterisk or FreeSWITCH, it is important
      to consider which community is more sustainable in the long term.</para>

      <para>Many people have their own thoughts and feelings about this.
      It may well be that the existence of both competing products with
      distinct communities is the most sustainable solution for both.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="pbx-asterisk-or-freeswitch-scalability-and-code-quality">
      <title>Scalabiltiy and code quality</title>

      <para>One of the reasons that FreeSWITCH was founded is because the
      creators were not satisfied with the design of Asterisk and did not
      feel that Asterisk would change.  FreeSWITCH was written from the
      ground up to address some of those perceived problems.</para>

      <para>One area where such problems exist is in the case of scalability.
      FreeSWITCH's design is more favorable to large scale operation.</para>

      <para>It should be noted that while the designers of FreeSWITCH have
      chosen to emphasize different priorities and achieved a more
      scalable solution, Asterisk has involved in other ways and some
      people feel the range of features Asterisk offers for developing their
      customized applications is superior and more relevant to them
      than scalability.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="pbx-asterisk-with-repro">
    <title>Using Asterisk with the repro SIP proxy</title>

    <para>Setup the SIP proxy as described in
    <xref linkend="sip-proxy-repro"/>.  Add a UDP transport in
    <literal>repro.config</literal>, it will be used to communicate with
    Asterisk.  It is a good idea to ensure that the firewall prevents external
    hosts from sending any UDP traffic to either the SIP proxy or the SIP port
    on Asterisk.</para>

    <para>Go to the repro web administration page and click to add a route.
    Configure the route using the details in
    <xref linkend="pbx-aterisk-with-repro-route"/>.  Replace
    <literal>A.B.C.D</literal> with the IP address of the Asterisk server.
    </para>

    <table xml:id="pbx-aterisk-with-repro-route">
      <title>repro route configuration</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*" />
        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*" />

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry align="center">Parameter</entry>
            <entry align="center">Value</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>URI</entry>
            <entry><literal>^sip:([0-9]*)@sip-proxy\.example\.org;.*transport=tls</literal></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Destination</entry>
            <entry><literal>sip:$1@A.B.C.D:5060;transport=udp</literal></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>Notice that this route looks for the <literal>transport=tls</literal>
    parameter.  This means it will only be applied to calls coming from the
    users.  When a call comes into the SIP proxy from the Asterisk server,
    it will be coming over the UDP transport and it won't be matched by
    this route (otherwise it would go into a loop).</para>

    <para>Next, in the repro web administration page, click to add an
    entry to the ACL.  Add an entry permitting packets from the IP address
    and SIP port used by the Asterisk server.</para>

    <para>Remember to restart the repro SIP proxy if changes were made to the
    list of domains or the <literal>repro.config</literal> file.</para>

    <para>In the Asterisk server, setup the <literal>sip.conf</literal> file
    as demonstrated in <xref linkend="pbx-aterisk-with-repro-sip.conf"/>.
    In particular, replace <literal>A.B.C.D</literal> with the IP address that the Asterisk
    server should bind to, this must be a routable IP address on the Asterisk
    host.</para>

    <example xml:id="pbx-aterisk-with-repro-sip.conf">
      <title>Asterisk <literal>sip.conf</literal></title>
      <programlisting format="linespecific">; should match the realm used by the proxy
realm=sip-proxy.example.org
domain=sip-proxy.example.org
fromdomain=sip-proxy.example.org
port=5060
bindaddr=A.B.C.D

; follow this pattern to define a user
[8001]
username=8001
secret=whatever
host=dynamic
canreinvite=no
mailbox=8001
nat=yes</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>The Asterisk server will need to be able to send calls to SIP users who
    are registered with the SIP proxy.  The calls can be routed using the
    <literal>Dial</literal> command as demonstrated in
    <xref linkend="pbx-aterisk-with-repro-extensions.conf"/>.</para>

    <example xml:id="pbx-aterisk-with-repro-extensions.conf">
      <title>Asterisk <literal>extensions.conf</literal></title>
      <programlisting format="linespecific">exten => _8XXX,n,Dial(SIP/${EXTEN}@sip-proxy.example.org,45)</programlisting>
    </example>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
