<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
      xml:id="pstn">
  <title>PSTN connectivity</title>

  <para>The Public Switched Telephone Network (PSTN) remains pervasive
  and convenient for much of the world's population, even though it is
  also expensive, unsophisticated and insecure.</para>

  <para>In the early days of IP telephony, the PSTN was perceived
  as something of a security blanket.  Companies would design their IP
  telephony system to mirror the traditional PBX.  Some would even keep a
  few analog phone lines connected in case of an "emergency".</para>

  <para>This fear-based approach has gradually been replaced by a more
  pragmatic approach, relegating the PSTN services to being just one
  part of the big picture.  A modern RTC-based solution works seamlessly
  with or without the PSTN.</para>

  <para>The emotional attachment to the PSTN has largely been contained
  due to two factors: the widespread presence of smartphones as an
  alternative means of communication that can be used in an emergency
  and the increased investment in corporate IT networks which need to
  be always available.</para>

  <para>This chapter looks at PSTN connectivity issues.</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>Methods of PSTN connectivity</title>

    <para>Anybody, anywhere in the world, can now rent inbound phone
    numbers and make outgoing calls using SIP trunking providers.
    This is often the fastest, cheapest and most flexible means of
    getting connected to the PSTN.  It is often possible to port
    existing phone numbers from legacy phone companies to SIP operators.
    </para>

    <para>There are a range of hardware options for joining analog and
    ISDN telephone lines to an IP network.  One option is to purchase
    a dedicated media gateway, such as the those promoted
    by Cisco Systems and other well known vendors.  Another option is
    to install an ISDN or analog telephony card into a server and
    run Asterisk or FreeSWITCH, as described in <xref linkend="pbx"/>,
    configured solely to act as a media gateway.</para>

    <para>If dedicated ISDN links to the telephone company are important,
    it is worthwhile considering one further permutation: instead of
    installing the media gateway at the office location, have the ISDN
    lines installed to a rack in a data center and use VPN or WAN links
    from the data center to the office.  This can achieve higher resilience
    and flexibility: if the main office site suffers from any kind of
    technical or environmental disturbance, calls can be routed from
    the data center to users at home, on mobile devices or at another
    branch office or disaster recovery location.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title><emphasis>ingress</emphasis> call handling</title>

    <para>The concept of an <emphasis>ingress</emphasis> module
    accepting calls from other places such as SIP trunks or ISDN trunks
    is introduced in <xref linkend="rtc-architecture-routing"/>.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis>ingress</emphasis> stage should, in most cases,
    normalize both the destination number and the caller ID into the E.164
    format.  This will assist with both routing and log analysis later on.
    </para>

    <para>The <emphasis>ingress</emphasis> stage may also convert the
    destination numbers to the addresses of internal users such as
    <literal>user@example.org</literal>.  This can also be done at
    the routing stage.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title><emphasis>egress</emphasis> call handling</title>

    <para>The concept of <emphasis>egress</emphasis> modules preparing calls
    from the local users to go out to SIP trunks or ISDN trunks
    is also introduced in <xref linkend="rtc-architecture-routing"/>.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis>egress</emphasis> stage should convert the
    destination number into the format expected by the telephone
    company or trunking provider.  For example, they may require a
    <literal>00</literal> prefix on all numbers qualified with a country
    code.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis>egress</emphasis> stage is also a good place to
    set the caller ID.  Some trunking providers automatically set the
    caller ID for you.  Some allow you to specify the caller ID
    in the <literal>From</literal> header, as long as the value you
    use is an inbound number that you have purchased from the same company.
    If you try to use any other number, it is likely the will replace
    it with one of your numbers selected at random.  ISDN trunks
    attached to a soft PBX or media gateway also permit the caller ID
    number to be set on a per-call basis.</para>

    <para>Setting the caller ID to a constant value is relatively
    easy within an Asterisk extension as demonstrated in
    <xref linkend="pstn-asterisk-set-caller-id"/>.</para>

    <example xml:id="pstn-asterisk-set-caller-id">
      <title>Asterisk <literal>extensions.conf</literal> for specifying caller ID</title>
      <programlisting linenumbering="numbered">exten => _X.,1,Set(CALLERID(name)=00442071358378)
exten => _X.,2,Set(CALLERID(number)=00442071358378)</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>Instead of hard-coding a constant value, if the users
    have their own direct phone numbers, a CSV file or Asterisk Realtime
    SQL lookups could be used to map individual SIP usernames to personal
    caller-ID values.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Emergency calls</title>

    <para>Providing access to dial the emergency services has been
    a controversial issue for all IP-based telephony.  Users
    may see a phone and want to use it to make such a call.
    Anybody installing phones should contemplate what happens in
    this situation.</para>

    <para>The first thing to note is that not all organizations route
    emergency calls to the publicly operated emergency call center.
    Some large organizations and universities route these calls to
    their internal security office.  The suitability of this approach
    depends on local laws and the training of the security staff.
    </para>

    <para>Many SIP providers now offer an option to handle emergency
    calls.  For this to be effective, the SIP provider usually needs to
    have accurate records of the addresses where the SIP trunks are
    used.  For example, care needs to be taken to ensure that emergency calls
    are not routed from mobile VoIP users when they are off-site, as
    the emergency services may arrive at the wrong location.</para>

    <para>Another option is to have a single physical phone line or
    GSM SIP gateway attached to the IP phone system solely for routing
    emergency calls.  All other calls would be routed to the normal
    SIP providers.</para>

    <para>If it is not technically feasible to route calls to the
    emergency service number, it may be useful to provide a brief
    recorded message telling the user to call emergency services from
    another phone.  After playing the message once or twice, the
    PBX should hang up, so the user knows that the call is not being
    routed.</para>

    <para>In the early days of telephony, not every home or office
    had a telephone.  In Britain, which is known for its distinctive
    red phone boxes, the police force took responsibility for installing many
    <emphasis>blue</emphasis> phone boxes for use by police and people
    without a telephone.  Some people feel that it is important for the
    emergency services to be proactive again and ensure that emergency
    call centers have a presence on the Internet, accepting calls directly
    from users of SIP and XMPP.
    </para>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
