<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
      xml:id="user-authentication">
  <title>User and credential storage</title>

  <para>Most of the products described in this document, including
  SIP proxies, XMPP servers, TURN servers and soft PBXes offer a range
  of choices for maintaining a user database and storing user
  credentials.</para>

  <sect1 xml:id="user-authentication-credentials">
    <title>Credentials</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Password encryption</title>

      <para>It is not strictly necessary to use passwords for SIP, XMPP
      and TURN, you can use certificate authentication instead.
      Nonetheless, many people find that some of their users can only
      support password authentication or they don't want the complexity
      of managing public key infrastructure (PKI).</para>

      <para>XMPP transmits passwords in cleartext, so all XMPP
      connections should be secured with TLS to avoid eavesdropping.
      The benefit of this approach is that XMPP users can be
      authenticated against any type of pre-hashed passwords or using
      a method such as LDAP bind to verify the supplied credential.</para>

      <para>SIP and TURN use a DIGEST algorithm very similar to
      HTTP DIGEST.  The DIGEST algorithm requires the server to have
      either an unencrypted copy of the password, a password encrypted
      with the HA1 algorithm or a service (such as RADIUS) that can
      perform delegated DIGEST authentication.</para>

      <para>If unencrypted passwords are available, then the SIP and
      TURN servers can use them to construct the HA1 hash value or
      you can precompute the HA1 values and store them in a database.</para>

      <warning>
        <para>HA1 hash values should be considered as sensitive as
        unencrypted values.  Even though the plaintext password can't
        be recovered in a simple manner, anybody in possession of the
        HA1 value is able to use it to construct a response to a HTTP
        or SIP DIGEST challenge, thereby impersonating the user who
        owns that password.  Therefore, do not keep HA1 hash values in
        world-readable configuration files or publicly accessible in
        LDAP.</para>
      </warning>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>HA1 in detail</title>

      <para>The HA1 hash includes the username, the password and the realm.
      A HA1 hash can be easily constructed at the UNIX command line
      as demonstrated in <xref linkend="auth-make-ha1"/>.</para>

      <example xml:id="auth-make-ha1">
        <title>Computing HA1</title>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">$ echo -n "alice:example.org:secret" | md5sum
543e1aec5d3614f03141652d6ada51b2  -
$ echo -n "alice@example.org:example.org:secret" | md5sum
1441a999b257bcd0cf5166930039876a  -</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>In both examples, the realm is <code>example.org</code>.</para>

      <para>In the first case, the user authenticates using the
      username <code>alice</code>.  In the second case, the user
      authenticates using the username <code>alice@example.org</code>.
      This second permutation is referred to by some products as
      <emphasis>HA1B</emphasis>.  Some people prefer to use the full
      <emphasis>user@domain</emphasis> syntax to support virtual hosting
      with a single <emphasis>realm</emphasis> value on a single SIP
      proxy or TURN server.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="user-authentication-databases">
    <title>Databases</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>RADIUS</title>

      <para>IETF <code>draft-sterman-aaa-sip-04</code> describes a
      mechanism for RADIUS servers to participate in a SIP DIGEST
      challenge/response without the SIP proxy having a copy of the
      password or HA1 value at all.  This is implemented by the
      <emphasis>FreeRADIUS</emphasis> project in the module
      <link xlink:href="http://wiki.freeradius.org/modules/Rlm_digest">
      <code>rlm_digest</code></link> and supported by all the major
      SIP proxy servers.</para>

      <para>At the time of writing, work is in progress to enable RADIUS
      to participate in TURN authentication in the same way.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>LDAP</title>

      <para>If LDAP is in use, you may wish to consider storing the
      HA1 values in the LDAP directory.  Each time a user is created
      or a user changes their password, the LDAP server will need to
      update the HA1 hash as well as updating any other copies of the
      password hashed with other algorithms.</para>

      <para>For example, the <emphasis>OpenLDAP</emphasis> server
      allows such logic to be implemented in an overlay, this is
      already demonstrated in the <emphasis>smbk5pwd</emphasis> module
      for hashing copies of the user's password in various algorithms
      used by Windows.</para>

      <para>Due to the sensitive nature of the HA1 values, they
      should be stored in an attribute that is not readable to any
      other user or anonymous access.  <xref linkend="openldap-acl-ha1"/>
      demonstrates how to protect the <code>ha1Password</code> so it can
      only be read by a user
      <code>cn=sip-proxy,dc=example,dc=org</code>.</para>

      <example xml:id="openldap-acl-ha1">
        <title><emphasis>OpenLDAP</emphasis> ACL for protecting
        <code>ha1Password</code></title>

        <programlisting format="linespecific">    access to attr=ha1Password
        by self =xw
        by dn="cn=sip-proxy,dc=example,dc=org" read
        by anonymous auth
        by * none </programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>LDAP can also be used to assist in routing as described in
      <xref linkend="enum"/>.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="user-authentication-sql">
      <title>SQL databases</title>

      <para>Many RTC products have some capability to interact with an
      SQL database to obtain user credentials, configuration settings
      and routing information.</para>

      <para>Each product has a different schema, however, it is possible
      to create a user list table that aggregates all the columns
      required to satisfy multiple RTC servers.  For example, a single
      user list table can be created for use by <emphasis>Asterisk</emphasis>
      and <emphasis>repro</emphasis>.  <emphasis>repro</emphasis> simply
      ignores many of the columns used by <emphasis>Asterisk</emphasis>.</para>

      <sect3 xml:id="user-authentication-sql-setup-postgresql">
        <title>Setting up PostgreSQL for SIP users</title>

        <para>The packages for the <emphasis>repro</emphasis> SIP proxy
        include SQL schema files for creating tables.
        <xref linkend="postgresql-install-debian"/> demonstrates how
        to install the <emphasis>PostgreSQL</emphasis> server package.
        <xref linkend="postgresql-setup-debian"/> demonstrates how
        to use the <code>createdb</code> command to create a database
        called <code>repro</code> and use the <code>psql</code>
        command to log in as the <emphasis>DBA</emphasis> and
        create a user called <code>repro</code> for the SIP proxy.
        The final <code>psql</code> command uses the schema file
        to create the tables.</para>

        <example xml:id="postgresql-install-debian">
          <title>Install <emphasis>PostgreSQL</emphasis> on Debian or Ubuntu</title>
          <programlisting format="linespecific">$ sudo apt-get install postgresql postgresql-client</programlisting>
        </example>

        <example xml:id="postgresql-setup-debian">
          <title>Configure PostgreSQL</title>
          <programlisting format="linespecific">$ sudo su - postgres
postgres$ createdb repro
postgres$ psql
postgres=# create user repro password 'abc';
postgres=# \q
postgres$ exit
$ su vi /etc/postgresql/9.4/main/pg_hba.conf
$ su systemctl restart postgresql
$ psql -U repro -W repro &lt; /usr/share/doc/repro/create_postgresql_reprodb.sql</programlisting>
        </example>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Product-specific file formats</title>

      <para>Each product also supports some native file formats.
      For example, <emphasis>repro</emphasis> can store user data in
      <emphasis>Berkeley DB</emphasis> files while
      <emphasis>Asterisk</emphasis> can store users in the
      <code>sip.conf</code> text file.  The <emphasis>Prosody</emphasis>
      XMPP server can store its data in JSON files.  In some cases, the
      files are maintained by the administrator using a text editor and
      in other cases they are updated at runtime by the application.</para>

      <para>To eliminate the risk of runtime dependencies on databases,
      it is relatively straightforward to create a script that
      periodically extracts user data from a database and creates files
      for the relevant processes to consume.  If one of the processes has
      to start up or continue operating during a database outage, it will
      be able to do so using the last copy of the file.</para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="user-authentication-conclusion">
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>A guide like this can't proscribe the correct solution for
    every scenario.  This chapter simply aims to raise awareness of all
    the options for storing usernames and credentials and making them
    accessible to RTC processes.  System administrators and developers
    will need to consider the infrastructure that is already present
    when deciding which of these options are most relevant for a given
    site.</para>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
