<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
      xml:id="voip-fraud">
  <title>Mitigating VoIP fraud risk</title>

  <para>VoIP fraud is not a new problem, it is just an old problem with a new
  target.  Fraud is not a reason to avoid VoIP and RTC technology.  Fraud
  has been a regular problem for companies with traditional ISDN phone systems.
  Managing the risk requires a balanced approach.</para>

  <sect1 xml:id="voip-fraud-insurance">
    <title>Legal insurance</title>

    <para>In the event that your phone account is misused, you may end up in
    a legal dispute with your phone company.  Check that you have a
    satisfactory legal costs insurance policy.  Verify that the terms and
    conditions include cover for disputes with utility companies.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="voip-fraud-trade-body-membership">
    <title>Trade body membership</title>

    <para>If you are operating a business, are you a member of any trade
    organizations, such as the local chamber of commerce?</para>

    <para>These organizations sometimes provide useful advice and
    sometimes arrange legal insurance on behalf of members.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="voip-fraud-set-credit-limit">
    <title>Set a credit limit</title>

    <para>If you leave the cookies out on the table, it won't be long until
    children start eating them and they will keep eating until they are all
    gone. Likewise, if your VoIP PBX is hacked, the bad guys are going to use
    it to relay calls to high cost destinations: <emphasis>and they are not
    going to stop until you switch the system off or the phone company cuts
    the line</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>The number one thing you can do to protect your phone system does
    not involve any technical changes. It simply involves writing a letter.
    </para>

    <para>Write to your phone company and tell them the amount of daily and
    monthly expenditure you authorise. Make it clear that this is both a
    security precaution and that any severe violation may jeopordise your
    business to the extent that you may not be able to pay bills in future.
    </para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>Dear Sir,</para>

      <para>My phone number is ___________ and my account number
      is ____________</para>

      <para>I am writing to inform you that the total authorized expenditure
      for this account is $_______ per day and $________ per month.</para>

      <para>Any services supplied in excess of this authorization will be
      treated as if they were supplied in error and we accept no liability for
      them.</para>

      <para>Furthermore, I am informing you that we explicitly do not require
      the use of any of the services listed below, that the supply of these
      services is not authorized and that if any of these services are
      supplied to us or billed to us without management authorization,
      it is an error of the phone company and therefore it will not be paid.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>Calls to premium rate numbers</listitem>
        <listitem>Reverse charge calls charged at a rate in excess of $___ per minute</listitem>
        <listitem>Calls to numbers where a share of the call charge is paid out to the recipient of the call (such as the UK 0871 numbers)</listitem>
        <listitem>Premium-rate text messaging services</listitem>
        <listitem>Data roaming charges</listitem>
        <listitem>Data charges for data usage in excess of bundled data allowances</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>This letter has been sent to you by recorded delivery and takes
      effect on receipt.</para>

      <para>Sincerely,</para>

      <para>____________________</para>

      <para>Director/Manager/President</para>

    </blockquote>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="voip-fraud-use-distinct-inbound-service">
    <title>Use a different phone company for inbound numbers</title>

    <para>If you do ever end up with an inflated bill that has come about
    because of illegal use of your VoIP system, and if your phone company
    has somehow lost the letter you sent specifying your maximum authorized
    expenditure, they might try and bully you into paying the bill anyway.
    </para>

    <para>Phone companies have large accounts departments that are very
    experienced at manipulating and bullying customers to pay a bill whether
    it is correct or not. A recent report by analysts Juniper Research
    suggested that phone companies lose over $58 billion per year due to
    their own technical faults in billing technology. The magnitude of this
    figure emphasises one particular point: phone companies may sometimes
    underbill you, they may sometimes overbill you, but if customers were
    watching their bills more closely, phone companies wouldn't be making so
    many mistakes.</para>

    <para>With such unreliable systems, the phone company has very little
    evidence they can rely on to force you to pay a bill. So they simply cut
    off customer's numbers.</para>

    <para>This is why this point is so vital: use two different phone
    companies.</para>

    <para>All your outgoing calls go through one company (company A).</para>

    <para>All your phone numbers and incoming calls come through a different
    company (company B).</para>

    <para>If your VoIP system is hacked or misused in some way, company A
    might cut off your line - but you will still be receiving incoming
    calls normally thanks to company B.</para>
  </sect1>
</appendix>
